Rafael Cassemiro Freire

H1B Visa - Contagem/MG | (31)9966-6210 | rafaelcfreire@gmail.com | Skype: rafael.freire1983

About me

I have been working with software development for about 7 years. During this time I have had the opportunity to work in projects of different sizes, scope and goals. Most of this time as an adopter of JEE architecture and related implementations being focused on Spring framework solutions (MVC, DI). Currently I am studying functional approach, which is helping me towards achieving high quality code and define concise patterns of coding. I am a very enthusiastic in topics related with metrics of quality in code and usually write about it in my personal blog where I describe some of my experience in software development. My main objective in career nowadays is to work and contribute with definitions in a company where coding quality is essential and practiced in everyday tasks, not just a buzzword.

Education

INSTITUTO DE GESTAO DE TECNOLOGIA DA INFORMAÇÃO

Post Graduation in Software Architecture Strategies

UNIVERSITY PONTIFICIA UNIVERSIDADE CATOLICA - MINAS GERAIS

Bachelor in Information Systems 2004-2009

Certifications

- IBM Certified Solution Designer Object Oriented Analysis and Design, vUML 2.
- IBM Certified Solution Designer IBM Rational Unified Process v7.0
- Oracle Certified Professional Java SE Programmer 82% achievement
- ETS TOEIC

Work Experience

MANUSCRIPT REVIEWER | MANNING PUBLICATIONS | CURRENT

I am working as a manuscript reviewer in new publishings of Manning Publications. This is a specific review before the book is released, I am responsible for reading the text, executing the code examples, finding errors and possible points of misunderstanding. My last contribution was in "Functional Reactive Programming in Action" released in 2015.

SYSTEMS ANALYST | UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE MINAS GERAIS | CURRENT - 05/2013

I develop a Java EE system for the public healthcare in Brazil. These systems are responsible for calculation of taxes and budgets for states according to states' demand. Furthermore, this application is a Web transactional system, using JSF 2.0 and Richfaces for the UI, Spring framework as transactional controller and Hibernate as ORM. I work directly with definitions of code quality patterns and Sonar to ensure the level of quality in the project.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER | AVENUE CODE LLC | 08/2011 - 05/2013

I worked as a backend developer for the cliente Macy's. It was a Product Information System using Spring MVC as main framework for view and Controller layers and Hibernate as a repository layer. In this project we extensively used TDD during creation of new stories. Another relevant contribution I made was in a media integration for macys.com that was planned for users world wide. The tech stack was Facebook API focused in Javascript and JQuery.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER | ALGAR TECNOLOGIA/SYNOS TECHNOLOGIES | 09/2009 - 08/2011

Development of a system focused in control taxes for the Minas Gerais government. Using JEE5 platform with a proprietary framework called Unifw that mainly is a abstraction layer for EJB2.1, avoiding some of its workarounds and need for configuration files. In this project I was responsible for refactoring the core of the application that consists of heavy usage of remote transactions which improved the performance by 50 per cent in terms of memory usage and reduced the code complexity by 30%.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER | ADI SISTEMAS DE INFORMAÇÃO | 09/2009 - 02/2008

Development of a ERP focused in city hall's management. Based in a unified process and using the JEE5 spec mainly. The architecture is based on a three tier app with JSP, JavaBeans and JDBC, integration with third party software using SOAP(XML). Acted as tech leader in a specific module related with financial limits.

Portfolio

- Rafael Freire Tech Blog http://rafaelcfreire.github.io
- LinkedIn Profile
 http://www.linkedin.com/pub/rafael-freire/31/a31/332
- GitHub Profile https://github.com/rafaelcfreire
- BitBucket Profile https://bitbucket.org/rafaelcfreire
- CodePen page http://codepen.io/rafaelcfreire
- Article "Favorecendo a qualidade de código com analise estática" published in Java Magazine 109
 http://www.devmedia.com.br/codificando-com-selo-de-qualidade-revista-java-magazine-109/26309